There's different things you have to click. It's recording now. We're good?
So press stop broadcast, I think that means it started already. Good
morning. Today is March 3rd, it's the 5th of אדר. Adar. Today's
דף daf is בבא בתרא דף מ'. Bava Batra Daf Mem. We're
right on the top line of מ' עמוד ב' Mem Amud Beis
and we get to start a new topic, a little bit of
a new topic, continuation of the old topic, the topic about מחאה,
Machaa, objections to different claims, and מודעא, Modaa, admissions. Sorry,
we're on the last line of ל"ט עמוד ב'. Lamed Tes Amud
Beis. I'm sorry, I made a mistake. Okay, so אמר רבא אמר
רב נחמן. Amar Rava Amar Rav Nachman. רבא Rava quotes from רב
נחמן: Rav Nachman: מחאה בפני שנים. Machaa bifnei shnayim.
An objection to a claim, in this case we've been talking, it's
very important that the מרא קמא Mar-Kamma of any piece of property,
real estate, has to object to the חזקה Chazaka within the three
years, and that's been the main topic here. So in order to
register that מחאה, Machaa, the מחאה, Machaa, the objection has to be
in front of two witnesses. That makes sense, we have to have
a way of verifying it. What's important about that though is that
it doesn't need to be in front of the... first of all,
it doesn't need to be in front of three, that is, it
doesn't need to be in front of a בית דין. Beis Din.
It isn't a court proceeding as much as just registering a fact
on the book. And second, secondly, it doesn't have to be in
front of the בעל דבר. Ba'al Davar. You don't have to go
to the guy who's squatting on your land and object to him,
you just have to register the complaint with witnesses.
Now רבא Rava quotes from רב נחמן: Rav Nachman: מחאה בפני שנים
ואין צריך לומר כתבו. Machaa bifnei shnayim v'ein tzarich lomar kisvu. You
don't have to say go and write it, that is, they could
go write it without you having said please go write it for
me. Would they need to write it at all? So it technically
doesn't need to be written at all, but it would be much
more handy if he had a document, an authorized שטר Shtar that
said this objection, that they could pass off to the בית דין
Beis Din and the testimony was on record. So the idea of
having the testimony on record as a שטר Shtar would be very
handy and would be very useful for that original owner to not
only have registered it publicly but then have proof that that had
happened and to be able to have the court know about it
later. So the witnesses would be empowered to go write that שטר
Shtar without any explicit instruction. So the first explanation, maybe the easiest
explanation for that, we have to get into the question of what
is this מחאה? Machaa? Who is involved in making the מחאה? Machaa?
Normally we would say number one, we have two problems. The first
problem is how can you make a שטר Shtar if the person
you're arguing with doesn't agree to it? Usually a שטר Shtar requires
the consent of both parties because it increases the stakes of the
case. We know that a loan that's registered by a שטר Shtar
has a lot more power on lien than just a normal oral
loan,
and so the ability to create a שטר Shtar really does increase
the standing of the case. It would be something that you would
presumably the person you're arguing with would have to agree to. But
as the ראשונים Rishonim point out here, you can see in the
last תוספות Tosfos on ל"ט עמוד ב'... Lamed Tes Amud Beis... Of
course the person wouldn't agree. So exactly. So first of all he
doesn't agree, but second of all the מחאה Machaa is not really
between you and the other person. You actually don't care about what
the other party... all you're doing is registering your objection. There could
be who knows who, it doesn't matter who's the other party. In
his claim. Right. And so the point is it's not actually with
him. The second question we have is how can this שטר Shtar
work? Normally, right, well what's a שטר? Shtar? We would think a
שטר Shtar is basically taking oral testimony and writing it down, but
there's actually a prohibition seemingly to write down oral testimony. The גמרא
Gemara in other places learns out from the
פסוק: Pasuk: מפי שני עדים. mi-pi shnei eidim. So it says: מפיהם
ולא מפי כתבם. mi-pihem v'lo mi-pi kisavam. You can only take testimony
from the mouth of the witnesses and not from a written document.
So how can we even have such an institution of שטר Shtar
to begin with? So it's a much debated topic, but more or
less either you have to say that the שטר Shtar is some
kind of exception to that rule, or that's different when the בעל
דבר Ba'al Davar actually consents to it. If the person consents, then
it's not מפי כתבם, mi-pi kisavam, it's actually מפי כתבו. mi-pi kisavo.
It's as if the person is obligating themselves to do it, and
that's like הודאת בעל דין כמאה עדים דמי hoda'as ba'al din k'me'ah
eidim dami that we've seen; when you admit to something, that empowers
it to take effect. Wait which person are you referring to? The
person who's being claimed from normally, like if you owe me money,
right, and then I allow them to write it down. So that
means you've actually agreed to obligate yourself in that regard.
So that would be a case where your admission to the loan
empowers the שטר Shtar to have a meaning, but that's not because
of the witnesses, it's not מפי כתבם, mi-pi kisavam, it's מפי כתבו
mi-pi kisavo as you would have been the one to write it.
So how does that apply here? So here it also doesn't apply
because it doesn't make sense because there is no second party. So
that's part of the issue here. So that's part of the issue
here, but basically this is a way to take some kind of
oral testimony and turn it into a written document. Certainly sounds like
that problem of מפיהם ולא מפי כתבם, mipihem v'lo mipi chtavam,
so the רמב"ם's Rambam answer, the רמב"ם Rambam in הלכות עדות hilchot
edut I think, is that basically the whole institution of שטר shtar
is only מדרבנן. miderabbanan. So מדאורייתא mide'oraita there's a prohibition to write
down testimony. The Rabbis realized at some point that it was incredibly
impractical to only take oral testimony, and so they created this idea
of a written document that would have the strength of testimony. ספר
וחתום, sefer v'chatom, that sounds like a שטר. shtar. That's from ירמיהו.
Yirmiyahu. So okay, so it must have been the Rabbis in the
time of ירמיהו. Yirmiyahu. Okay. I'm just thinking God told him that.
But the other possibility is that that is a שטר קנין, shtar
kinyan, not a שטר shtar that's being used as proof. A שטר
קנין shtar kinyan to effect a sale, a bill of sale or
a גט get or a שטר קידושין shtar kiddushin or a שטר
שחרור shtar shichrur for a slave, something like that. All of those
שטרות shtarot are about transferring ownership. No one would debate the fact
that a גט get for example works at the דאורייתא de'oraita level.
The question is whether a שטר shtar that's written as proof could
have standing דאורייתא de'oraita or not. Does this enter the מחלוקת? machloket?
I was just trying to contextualize this. I would think that אין
לך מודעה גדולה מזו ein l'cha moda'ah gedolah mizu if I let's
say publish it in the paper and I'm not doing it in
front of anybody. Okay, but if he went to the town crier
and he told them 'spread the word', it's not just one person,
I would think that would be- Right, I don't have an answer
to that. It certainly sounds in real life like it would be,
but I'm not sure whether הלכה halacha would recognize it or not,
just because it doesn't have the same kind of formality, I'm not
sure.
Okay, let's continue.
Yeah, what'd you say about it was forbidden biblically to write? It
would be forbidden for witnesses to testify in writing rather than orally,
it seems like. So depending on how you understand that פסוק, pasuk,
does that apply to a שטר shtar or not, and then you
have to think about how do you understand the existence of the
שטר. shtar.
It might just be, according to רבינו תם, Rabbeinu Tam, the only
thing that comes to exclude is that a person who cannot speak,
someone who's mute, cannot be a witness. But everyone else could send
their writing. Oh, it's in this תוספות! Tosafot! Yeah, and that's what
I was going to say! It's on מ"ט עמוד א'. mem-tet amud
alef. רי ששמע מרבינו תם שנוהגים שלוחה ידי עדותם באיגרת לבית דין
וחשבי עדות. ri sheshama mi'rabbeinu tam shenohagim sholuchei yedei edutan b'iggeret l'veit
din v'chashvei edut.
This is in תוספות Tosafot on מ"ט עמוד א', mem-tet amud alef,
right towards the top. The first word in the line is רי,
ri, that רי ri who was the nephew of רבינו תם. Rabbeinu
Tam. The רי ri heard from רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam that there
was the מנהג minhag in רבינו תם's Rabbeinu Tam בית דין beit
din that people would send testimony in letters וחשבי עדות v'chashvei edut
because he would treat it as עדות edut because רבינו תם Rabbeinu
Tam understood that the only thing excluded by this principle of מפיהם
ולא מפי כתבם mipihem v'lo mipi chtavam is that a person who
is unable to speak cannot testify, but that a person who is
able to speak is a כשר kasher witness, could still send a
written testimony. And that they base off of the principle from the
גמרא Gemara כל הראוי לבילה אין בילה מעכבת
בו. kol haraui l'vila ein bila me'akevet bo. That if
that, this a principle by קרבנות, korbanot, but it's extended to many
different contexts, that if you're, if it's a small enough quantity of
flour to bring a קרבן מנחה, korban mincha, then you don't actually
need to mix it with the oil. You can just put the
flour and pour the oil on top. But if it's too much
flour to be able to mix, more than forty סאה se'ah I
think, right? Is a very large quantity of flour. Then the principle
is then you're not able to mix it with the oil, and
therefore you would not be able to bring such a large קרבן
korban as a קרבן מנחה korban mincha because you would be unable
to mix. So you don't actually ever need to mix it, but
the being able or unable to mix is the requisite determining factor
for how large a קרבן מנחה korban mincha you could bring. And
that becomes a principle in general that sometimes things where there's something
necessary, it's not actually necessary to do that action. So here רבינו
תם Rabbeinu Tam said okay, if you're able to testify orally, then
you don't actually need to testify orally. It's just a requirement for
who comes to be the witness. This is a good source for
disability by the way, because you could actually, you think in a
modern sensibility you'd argue the opposite, a person who can't speak but
could write should be given an accommodation, and he'd have the accommodation.
I would include this source.
It's an interesting source, certainly. Okay, so continue on מ"ט עמוד א'.
mem-tet amud alef. But still, you know, we're able to speak but
can't walk and can't get to the בית המדרש beit hamidrash still
be- Right, so according to רבינו תם Rabbeinu Tam or people who
live far away or people who, right, or some other situation, then
they would still be able to send their testimony. So again, it's
a practical accommodation as well, if people live far apart and you
have a broader jurisdiction for your בית דין beit din and you
need to be able to get people's testimony even if they're far
away, it becomes very practical. That wouldn't work for things like ראש
חודש. Rosh Chodesh. It wouldn't work for things like ראש חודש. Rosh
Chodesh. Right. So which types of עדות edut does this apply to
seems to be mostly about monetary cases and much less about other
kinds of things. Okay. The גמרא Gemara continues, still רבא Rava quoting
רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, מודעה בפני שנים. moda'ah bifnei shnayim. Exactly. We
still wouldn't kill this guy. You can't kill someone by a שטר.
shtar. Correct. Okay. So a מודעה moda'ah is something that many of
us do every year. A מודעה moda'ah is when you're about to
do something, but you want everyone to know that when you're going
to be Forced, or you don't really mean it when you do
it. So we do it when we do התרת נדרים. Hatarat Nedarim.
At the end of the התרת נדרים, Hatarat Nedarim, there's a מנהג
minhag to submit a מודעא modaah to the בית דין Beit Din
to say, just so you know, any נדר neder I take from
now until the next year, actually we don't say that, we just
say from now forever. So we do it every year for no
reason based on the גמרא Gemara that says, which may also be
the source for כל נדרי, Kol Nidre, that if you want to
make a תנאי tenai מראש השנה me'Rosh Hashanah from the beginning of
the year that would apply for the whole year to annul your
vows proactively, you could do something like that. So a מודעא modaah
is a proactive objection or admission of coercion. So the
רשב"ם's Rashbam example on the first line, מי שאנסוהו למכור וליתן שלא
בעל כרחו, mi she'ansuhu limkor u-leiten shelo be-al korcho, someone forces you
to sell something. We're going to come up next week, we're going
to have a lot of סוגיות sugyot about people being forced to
sell things. So someone's forcing you to sell something. So before you
go and do the sale, you make another, you register your testimony
with two witnesses and they can write a שטר shtar
that you're actually being forced. So מודעא בפני שנים ואין צריך לומר
כתובו. modaah bifnei shnayim ve'ein tsarich lomar ketovu. You also don't need
to authorize them to write it. They're allowed to write it without
any explicit authorization because the assumption is that that's something beneficial to
you. The רשב"ם's Rashbam explanation for why these two, מחאה mecha'ah and
מודעא, modaah, do not need to be authorized
to write a שטר shtar is because there's no one who's at
a loss because of this. It's only beneficial to write it down.
So that's according to him the principle of
זכין לאדם שלא בפניו. zachin le'adam she'lo befanav. You can do something
beneficial to someone without them being present. I can get like a
good deal, let's say you're just, but he objected, the fact is
he objected in front of witnesses. Now the question is can the
witnesses write the שטר shtar without authorization? Right.
So writing the שטר shtar without authorization is זכין לאדם שלא בפניו.
zachin le'adam she'lo befanav. And we're going to see the next example.
It could be abused, like let's say I want to play the
market, you know, sell it to you, and I'm going to give
him a מודעא, modaah, I'm going to wait a year or whatever
it is until the market prices have gone up, I'm going to
re-trade you. Okay. Right. So there are other rules about מודעא modaah
and we're going to see some of them. There are ways in
which the מודעא modaah gets limited, particularly רב יוסף Rav Yosef towards
the bottom of the עמוד amud and also just the idea that
a מודעא modaah is still being made public. You're announcing it in
front of witnesses. It gets registered with the court presumably when they
write the שטר. shtar. So those kinds of things hopefully will prevent
people from abusing the system too much. But like any type of
legal system it's going to have mechanisms that could be abused in
one way or another. מודעא modaah might do something like that as
well. If you always make מודעות moda'ot and then you go around
selling things and buying things and all sorts of things,
at some point it's clear it needs to be, you have to
have a legitimate claim that you're actually being forced and it's not
just something you're doing to manipulate the other person. Okay. The third
example, הודאה בפני שנים ואין צריך לומר כתובו. hodaah bifnei shnayim ve'ein
tsarich lomar ketovu. הודאה, hodaah, an admission. I admit that I owe
someone a hundred dollars or I admit that I owe someone a
thousand dollars or that this is his piece of land or anything
like that. צריך לומר כתובו. tsarich lomar ketovu. You do have to
authorize the witnesses to write it down. Like I said before, in
a case of a loan or a debt, if it's not written,
if it's only an oral obligation, then it doesn't have the same
power to put a lien on your property as if it's written
in a שטר. shtar. A debt that's in a שטר shtar you
could collect from any properties that were sold after the time the
date written in the שטר. shtar. So an oral loan you can't
collect from any properties that were sold to have them on lien
because you don't know sort of when it was actually when it
took place. It's less formal, it's less binding, it has weaker power
in that sense. How would you translate the second category מודעא? modaah?
מודעא modaah is an objection or, I mean I don't know the
precise legal terms. It says admission here. An admission? No, that's a
הודאה. hodaah. That's the third one. Well מודעא modaah is an objection.
What's the difference between the מודעא modaah and the מחאה? mecha'ah? So
מחאה mecha'ah is you're on my land. A protest. A מחאה mecha'ah
is you're squatting on my land, it's my land. Right.
A מודעא modaah is tomorrow I know I'm going to be forced
to sell my land, so I want to register the fact with
the witnesses that I am being forced so that I can undo
that sale later.
Like someone is going to come to me with a gun. They'll
be over on the איסור issur of לא תחמוד lo tachmod and
they're going to take a gun and say please sell me your
apartment. Okay. And they pay me the money and I sign on
the dotted line, but I never agreed to it. I actually don't
want to do it. I'm being coerced. I'm being forced to do
something against my will. So if I had registered that complaint beforehand
with witnesses, then I would be able to undo that sale by
force of that מודעא. modaah. We're going to see on מ"ח Mem
Chet I think some of the discussions about forced sales, whether they
work or not, in general and other kinds of cases. So a
מודעה moda'a generally is a category that has to do with extortion
or forced sales. Some kind of coercion, right. That רשבם, Rashbam, the
first רשבם Rashbam on מ עמוד א. Mem Amud Aleph. Sorry, okay.
That's alright. Okay. So a הודאה hoda'a because there's another party involved,
there's a lender and a borrower, it can't be written without permission
because you can't say זכין לאדם שלא בפניו zachin le'adam shelo befanav
because it's going to obligate someone else, it creates a חוב, chov,
so it would be אין חבין לאדם שלא בפניו. ein chavin le'adam
shelo befanav. You can't put someone at a loss without their permission.
But it needs to be a little bit more than that because
in each of these cases that's somewhat true. The point is that
a מחאה mecha'a and a מודעה moda'a must be somehow more valid
without witnesses or equally valid with... No, it's not that they're valid
without witnesses, it's that they're valid without a שטר. shtar. They're equally
valid between orally and written. There's no increased power of the שטר,
shtar, it's just that the שטר shtar serves it is easier to
keep track of a שטר shtar than to find the witnesses one's
on vacation, I can't prove my case. This must not be the
case in the last case. Right. Okay. And now perhaps the more
most interesting one on the page, קנין בפני שנים. kinyan bifnei shnayim.
קנין, kinyan, here the גמרא, Gemara, when the גמרא Gemara says just
the word קנין kinyan by itself, it seems to refer to the
קנין חליפין, kinyan chalipin, the exchange, but not a barter type of
exchange but what we call the קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, which is
a symbolic exchange. We don't do that when we
sell חמץ? chametz? Only מדרבנן. miderabbanan. Well, one second. So this position
of רבא Rava and רב נחמן Rav Nachman is קנין בפני שנים.
kinyan bifnei shnayim. So קנין בפני שנים, kinyan bifnei shnayim, I'm going
to sell a field and I want to buy it by or
buy a field and I want to buy it by חליפין. chalipin.
I give my watch to the person who owns the field and
he sells me the whole field. The field must be worth, you
know, half a million dollars, but I can effect the transfer by
giving him my watch. That's a קנין חליפין kinyan chalipin and very
often he would probably give me back the watch. So according to
this position, קנין בפני שנים, kinyan bifnei shnayim, you would need to
do the קנין kinyan in front of two witnesses. Now that's unique
among any קנינים. kinyanim. We don't know any other קנינים, kinyanim, monetary,
financial transactions that would require witnesses. Usually you would just think the
two parties are involved, they agree to it. So who cares? Why
do you need witnesses to make a transaction? So we're going the
next line is crucial: ואין צריך לומר כתבו, ve'ein tzarich lomar kitvu,
and they don't have to be authorized to go write a שטר.
shtar.
So now again, if I'm buying a piece of land and I
bought it by חליפין, chalipin, I'm not going to have a שטר
shtar that says I own it, but the witnesses who witnessed the
transaction could go and write a שטר shtar that I own it
afterwards without being authorized. That's this line about קנין. kinyan. Okay. We're
going to come back... so רבא's Rava question is going to come
back in just one second, so let's pause... we'll keep going in
the גמרא, Gemara, and we'll come back to the question of קנין.
kinyan. קיום שטרות בשלושה, kiyum shtarot bishlosha, and קיום שטרות, kiyum shtarot,
that is, we know from the first פרק perek of גיטין, Gittin,
the whole process of verifying the witnesses on a שטר shtar and
the witnesses, particularly for a גט, get, they are in גיטין Gittin
but also for monetary שטרות, shtarot, has to be done in a
court. It's not something you can only do with witnesses, you actually
need the court to authorize. Okay.
And we have a סימן: siman: מ מ ה ק. Mem Mem
Hei Kof. קיום שטרות kiyum shtarot is an interesting question why you
need another one for... מחאה, mecha'a, מודעה, moda'a, הודאה, hoda'a, and קנין.
kinyan. So those are the four... and קיום שטרות, kiyum shtarot, but
it's not in the סימן. siman. Because because you need two, right,
you need three instead of two for that one. Right. So קיום
שטרות kiyum shtarot needs three. אמר רבא, amar Rava, רבא Rava says,
so this is now רבא Rava had quoted his teacher רב נחמן
Rav Nachman as having said all these things, and now רבא Rava
has a question: אי קשיא לי הא קשיא לי. i kashya li
ha kashya li. If I had a question, this would be the
question that I have. Which means this is a question. This is
my question, but he's saying it in a respectful way, to be
respectful of רב נחמן. Rav Nachman. So האי קנין היכי דמי, hai
kinyan heichi dami, what קנין kinyan are we talking about? אי כמעשה
בית דין דמי, ei kema'aseh beit din dami, if קנין kinyan is
like a court proceeding... okay, that's an interesting suggestion already too. So
if it is like a court proceeding, ליבעי תלתא, libei tlata, then
you should need three. If קנין kinyan is like a court proceeding,
if buying something with a חליפין chalipin needs a court, then you
need three.
ואי לא כמעשה בית דין דמי, ve'ei lo kema'aseh beit din dami,
and if it's not like a court proceeding, אמאי אינו צריך לומר
כתבו, amai einu tzarich lomar kitvu, then why wouldn't you need to
authorize the witnesses to write to write a שטר shtar because in
that case, the שטר shtar is going to give the person who
just bought it a stronger leg to stand on in terms of
ownership than if he didn't have the שטר? shtar? So it would
be חבין לו לאדם שלא בפניו chavin lo le'adam shelo befanav of
the original owner because the original owner sells something just by חליפין,
chalipin,
then until three years from now he can claim and protest and
there's... he's not going to have a שטר shtar to prove that
he bought it, it's going to be harder time for the purchaser.
So why would he give up that power to let the witnesses
write a שטר shtar without having authorized them? You're talking מטלטלין, metaltelin,
right? No, a field, usually, all land. So the there's no שטר
shtar for מטלטלין. metaltelin. Exactly. I just want to... you know, our
you buy a car and you have a car deed or a
car title... that's a שטר, shtar, that's our society has a שטר
shtar for that. I don't think הלכה halacha would really recognize such
a שטר shtar as having the same weight as a normal שטר.
shtar. So it's an interesting... So he's asking, so he had set
a question. If it's really something so powerful that it's like a
מעשה בית דין ma'aseh beis din and could be done against the
will of the person selling the field, then why don't you need
three to make it a court proceeding? And if it doesn't need
a three, if it's not like a court proceeding, then why does
the person selling the field not need to authorize the witnesses to
write the שטר? shtar? He'd be giving up something in them writing
a
שטר. shtar. Because the one buying it, what do you mean? But
the whole point is the person who would have to authorize the
witnesses. Obviously the person buying it wants the שטר. shtar. The question
is whether the person selling the field gives permission to write a
שטר shtar or not. And they say as long as you did
the קנין kinyan with two witnesses, you don't need to give them
explicit permission to write the שטר. shtar. It's as if he had
consented already. So what is רבא's Rava answer? So בתר דבעי הדר
פשטה. batar de'bayye hadar pashtei. After he had asked the question, he
answered his own question that it was a rhetorical question. לעולם לאו
כמעשה בית דין דמי. le'olam lav kema'aseh beis din dami. It is
not like a court proceeding. והכא היינו טעמא, vehacha hainu ta'ama, this
is the reason why he doesn't need to consent to give the
שטר. shtar. דמאי דאינו צריך לומר כותבו משום דסתם קנין לכתיבה עומד.
demai de'eino tzarich lomar koshvu mishum distam kinyan lechtiva omeid.
The reason he doesn't have to give explicit permission to write the
שטר shtar is because any קנין, kinyan, סתם קנין, stam kinyan, that
is even if you don't give permission, when you do a קנין
חליפין kinyan chalupin to sell something, you have implicitly authorized the witnesses
who saw that transaction to go write a שטר. shtar. Now this
is a big question. So רבי סולובייצ'יק Rabbi Soloveitchik and some of
his ancestors as well made a big deal about this. The fact
that the interconnection between the קנין חליפין kinyan chalupin and שטר. shtar.
Most קניינים kinyanim we think about,
חזקה hazakah on a field. I build a fence around the field
or I dig a hole in the field. Or משיכה, meshikha, I
buy an animal and I pull on the leash and I lead
it through the streets. Those are demonstrations of ownership in a real
way. I'm taking some object and actually showing that I am doing
to it what the person who owns it does. So normally a
קנין kinyan has some kind of an action which demonstrates ownership. With
קנין חליפין, kinyan chalupin, there's no demonstration of ownership. Michael, would you
sell me your car? And I give him a watch. That's not
any—but we're talking about real estate. For real estate, but we are
talking about מטלטלין? metaltelin?
It could be. חליפין chalupin could work for either one. Right, but
the point is that the action of חליפין chalupin is actually nothing
to do with the object being transferred. It's a totally separate process.
I'm giving you something and you're transferring ownership of something totally separate.
I feel like something's missing from it. If you were to give
this explanation in terms of the קנין סודר. kinyan sudar. That is
the קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, yeah. Wait, חליפין chalupin is an actual
bartered exchange, right? It's a מחלוקת machlokes what we're talking about
here. Because you know if I give you my goat and you
give me your doggy, right, that's an action that demonstrates just like
משיכה. meshikha. Right, because סודר sudar is just I picked up a
pen, what's that? Right, exactly. So is that what he's doing? Yeah,
we're talking about the קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, it seems like. סתם
קנין, stam kinyan, when they say קנין kinyan because it's the most
utilitarian of the קניינים. kinyanim. It's used in many different contexts, right?
It can be used for מטלטלין, metaltelin, it could be used for
land, it could be used for slaves, it could be used for
basically anything that requires a קנין, kinyan, with the important exception of
marriage and divorce. Marriage and divorce cannot be affected by a קנין
kinyan of a קנין סודר kinyan sudar because קנין סודר kinyan sudar
is fundamentally a financial transaction. It's one of the main proofs that
the role that קנין kinyan plays in קידושין kiddushin is actually not
a financial or monetary transaction. And that's discussed in קידושין דף ח.
Kiddushin Daf Ches.
So רבי סולובייצ'יק Rabbi Soloveitchik made a big deal about this and
suggested that the difference with חליפין chalupin and with שטר shtar as
opposed to other קניינים kinyanim is that they are about a demonstration
of consent by the parties involved. That normally with a transaction, you
have some level of consent obviously, otherwise it's being forced. But it's
actually it's only about the consent, it's only about the דעת da'as
involved and not about any other process. There's no action. You're talking
about קנין אנה כתובה. kinyan ana kesuva. Right, the קנין אנה כתובה,
kinyan ana kesuva, the rabbi says, is a demonstration of consent, of
obligation of the terms in the contract. So fundamentally the world we're
in is entirely a mental space. We're not doing any physical action
that actually demonstrates ownership and for that reason it has different rules,
like maybe it would require witnesses. Maybe one can transfer into the
other. That is סתם קנין לכתיבה עומד. stam kinyan lechtiva omeid. If
you did a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, you could write it as
a שטר shtar later if there were witnesses. And many other examples.
I just want to bring one example, he's telling... what's he trying
to do? He's trying to explain what?
Explain the fundamental difference between קנין סודר kinyan sudar and other קניינים
kinyanim and שטר shtar and other קניינים kinyanim and why שטר shtar
and קנין סודר kinyan sudar are so closely related. Why would you
say סתם קנין לכתיבה עומד? stam kinyan lechtiva omeid? And the reason
is because because they're both fundamentally about pure דעת da'as without any
action. And therefore and therefore it's a very different type of קנין.
kinyan. It's only about... What's the other example? A שטר. shtar. A
שטר shtar is also only about דעת, da'as, right? If I write
down a שטר, shtar, right? So both of them are the same
world. Other קנינים kinyanim inhabit one world, and קנין סודר kinyan sudar
and the שטר shtar inhabit another. Okay, meanwhile it still has to
be done in front of two, so we're all doing חמץ chametz
tomorrow. Ah, so the other issue is that the way we sell
the חמץ chametz and things like that doesn't really need a קנין.
kinyan. All you're doing is authorizing the rabbi to be your שליח.
shaliach. To make a שליח shaliach doesn't need a קנין, kinyan, but
I'll read you from the רמב"ם Rambam if I can find it.
The רמב"ם... Rambam... I'm going to read you, I'm going to tell
you.
This is the רמב"ם. Rambam.
The רמב"ם Rambam in פרק ה' perek hey in הלכות מכירה hilchos
mechira says, יש דברים הרבה שאין צריכים קנין ואין לקנין בהם טעם.
yesh dvarim harbeh she'ein tzerichim kinyan v'ein lakinyan bahem ta'am. There are
things that קנין kinyan does nothing and there's no purpose. כגון המשחרר
עבדו kegon hamishachrer avdo if you free your slave, או המגרש את
אשתו o hamigaresh es ishto if you give a גט, get, או
העושה שליח o ha'oseh shaliach if you appoint a שליח shaliach to
do something, או המוסר מודעה, o hamoser moda'ah, או המקבל מודעה, o
hamikabel moda'ah, או המוחל לחברו חוב o hamochel l'chavero chov you forgive
a loan, או פקדון שיש לו בידו. o pikadon she'yesh lo b'yado.
כל כיוצא בדברים אלו נהגו רוב המקומות להקנות במקצת אלו הדברים בקנין.
kol k'yotzei b'devarim eilu nahagu rov hamakomos l'haknot b'miktzas eilu hadvarim b'kinyan.
Nonetheless, even though there's no purpose in doing a קנין, kinyan, that
he means קנין סודר kinyan sudar in those situations, nonetheless people do
it anyway to create a context that feels more formal. So when
you authorize the rabbi to be your שליח shaliach to sell your
חמץ, chametz, you're just making a שליח, shaliach, you do it with
a קנין kinyan because it creates this sense of concretized consent in
some informal way because it's not actually necessary. A שליח shaliach you
could just make by saying, "Mike, would you please be my שליח?"
shaliach? instead of filling out a form online and being done with
it. Exactly. So that becomes part of this question of filling a
form out online. Can you appoint a שליח shaliach online? Why not?
If you call the rabbi on the phone maybe it's better. Online
there's no actual conversation going on between you and him and you
like click it. And so that's part of this interesting question and
that gets into this question of מכירת חמץ mechirath chametz and we
don't have to do it now. We have a month and a
half. This came up with 9/11 people were faxing or texting or
emailing the rabbis, "write my wife a גט, get, I may not
make it out of here." Right, the problem of writing a גט
get by email. I think Rabbi Jachter in the תחומין Techumin has
a whole article about can you authorize witnesses to write a גט
get by phone and things like that. It's a major question nowadays
obviously so many cases where if a husband and wife are living
in different countries and things like that and have been separated for
a long time, how are you able to authorize the גט get
in those cases. The רמב"ם, Rambam, I just want to point out,
the מחלוקת... machloket...
Well if he dies you don't need a גט. get. But what
if he's trapped and they don't know whether he's dead or not
and they take months to identify bodies
or if there's no...
Okay, so the רמב"ם Rambam in פרק כ"ט perek chaf tes in
הלכות מכירה hilchos mechira talks about the קנין, kinyan, the קנין סודר.
kinyan sudar. יראה לי שקטן שקנה קרקע yera'eh li she'katan she'kana karka
if a קטן katan bought land. How can he do that? The
רמב"ם Rambam discussed that earlier, it's possible for a קטן katan to
buy things if he knows his way around the marketplace, things like
that. But what if a קטן katan bought land ונתן דמים והחזיק
תעמוד בידו אף על פי שאין ממכר בקרקע כלום שהקטן כמי שאינו
לפנינו הוא וזכין לאדם שלא לפניו. v'natan damim v'hechzik ta'amod b'yado af
al pi she'ein mimkar b'karka klum she'hakatan k'mi she'eino l'faneinu hu v'zachin
l'adam she'lo l'fanav. Not that one.
Sorry. Where are you reading?
I'm in the רמב"ם Rambam in פרק כ"ט. perek chaf tes. Oh
here we go. הלכה ט. halacha tes. Sorry I was reading the
wrong הלכה. halacha. The רמב"ם Rambam says, וכן אם קנה מיד הקטן
או השכיר מקום המטלטלין לחזור בו לא קנה הלוקח. v'chein im kana
miyad hakatan o hiskir mekom hametaltelin lachazor bo lo kana halokeach. So
if you're trying to do a transaction with a קטן katan by
קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, it doesn't work. The רמב"ם Rambam says, שאין
מוציאין מיד הקטן בדין, she'ein motzi'in miyad hakatan b'din,
you can't force a קטן katan in court because a קטן katan
can't go to court. ואין הקנין מיד הקטן כלום. v'ein hakinyan miyad
hakatan klum.
And there's no such thing as doing a קנין סודר. kinyan sudar.
Because it's not דעת. da'as. Exactly. He has no דעת. da'as. A
קטן katan can sell things or buy things by משיכה meshicha and
חזקה chazaka and other types of processes because a קטן katan who
knows his way around business dealings can do things that demonstrate ownership.
But to do a קנין סודר, kinyan sudar, the קטן katan lacks
דעת. da'as. There's no דעת. da'as. Right. שהקנין בשטר shehakinyan b'shtar
because קנין kinyan will translate into being able to write it with
a שטר. shtar. ואין העדים חותמין על שטר אדם גדול. v'ein ha'edim
chotmin al shtar adam gadol. You can only witnesses can only sign
a שטר shtar if it's from someone who has דעת. da'as. And
there's two different versions in the text in the רמב"ם, Rambam, is
it שהקנין בשטר shehakinyan b'shtar or שהקנין כשטר? shehakinyan k'shtar?
So that's part of that question but that gets us into the
question of the קנין סודר kinyan sudar and the שטר shtar and
the consent involved there and the fact that it's basically a קנין
kinyan that operates almost entirely based on a דעת da'as rather than
on any type of form. That's... פרק כ"ט perek chaf tes of
הלכות מכירה hilchos mechira הלכה ט. halacha tes. כ"ט ט. Kaph-tet-tet.
Okay. סתם כתיבה עומד. stam k'sivah omeid.
Okay. רבה ורב יוסף דאמרי תרווייהו, Rabba v'Rav Yosef d'amri tarvaihu, so
we have a רבה Rabba and רב יוסף Rav Yosef both agree,
לא כתבינן מודעא אלא אמאן דלא צאיי דינא. lo katbinan moda'ah ela
aman d'lo tzai dina.
So according to רבה Rabba and רב יוסף, Rav Yosef, you... not
write a מודעא moda'a *moda'a*, we said a מודעא moda'a. *moda'a* was
when you're protesting that you're being coerced.
So it has to have been, sorry, where was I?
Okay, that it has to be that it's not sort of being
objected to in court. The רשב"ם *Rashbam* says אמאן דלא ציית דינא
*aman delo tzayit dina*, סרבן בדין *sarvan bedin*. דציית דינא לימא ליה
*de'tzayit dina leima lei*, why didn't you protest in court?
So it's only if he refuses to go to court to address
the fact that he's being, that you're being coerced. But if you're
able to, the person you're accusing of coercing you, because otherwise you
could just talk about it in the court. Why do you have
to make this מודעא moda'a. *moda'a*? So they're limiting the circumstances in
which the מודעא moda'a *moda'a* would be applicable. Okay. אביי ורבא דאמרי
תרוייהו *Abaye veRava de'amri tarvaihu*, both אביי *Abaye* and רבא *Rava* agreed
to something. What did they both say? אפילו עלי ועלך *afilu alai
ve'alach*, even if he said it as אפילו עלי ועלך *afilu alai
ve'alach*. דציית דינא ראוי לכתוב עלינו מודעא moda'a. דזימנין דאין בית דין
מזומן מיד *de'tzayit dina ra'uy likhtov aleinu moda'a de'zimnin de'ein beis din
mezuman miyad*. So there are certain cases, so they push back one
way, רבה ורב יוסף *Rabba veRav Yosef* pushed one way, and then
רבא ואביי *Rava veAbaye* pushed back the other way and said, yeah,
it's אפילו עלי ועלך *afilu alai ve'alach*, that is, it's like it's
going to take too long to get to court or there's going
to be inconvenient, then you could make the מודעא moda'a, *moda'a* any
time. Okay. אמרי נהרדעי *Amri Nehardai*, then the נהרדעי *Nehardai* said, נהרדעי
*Nehardai* followed the opinions of שמואל *Shmuel*, but we don't know which
נהרדעי *Nehardai* it is. אמרי נהרדעי כל מודעא דלא כתיב בה אנן
ידעינן ביה באונסא דפלניא לאו מודעא היא *Amri Nehardai kol moda'a delo
ketiv ba anan yadinan beh be'onsa de'planya lav moda'a hi*.
Okay. If it doesn't say "we know that פלוני *Ploni* is being
forced," it doesn't count as a מודעא *moda'a*. That is, if the
מודעא *moda'a* is just פלוני *Ploni* told us that he's being forced,
that doesn't count as a good מודעא *moda'a*. That's just I'm writing
down a שטר shtar *shtar* that says somebody told me something. But
how would they know other than him telling them? So they would
have to have actually witnessed some kind of coercion. They would have
to have seen someone threaten him, see someone pressure him. That's a
whole different thing. It's not like they go to two guys and
say "I happen to know tomorrow." Right. Those two guys have to
be in a closet peeking through. Right. Something like that. Or at
least אונס גמור יש לו *ones gamur yesh lo*, ומכירין אנו איזה
אונס *u'makirin anu eizeh ones*, we know something is going on. It
has to be so public or so real that they're actually aware
of it and that it's not just hearsay based on this guy.
Okay. So מודעא דמאי *moda'a de'mai*, what מודעא *moda'a* are we talking
about? אי דגיטא ודמתנתא *i degitta udemataneta*, is it a מודעא *moda'a*,
an objection to a גט *get* or to giving a מתנה *matana*?
גילויי מלתא בעלמא היא *giyui milta be'alma hi*, that's just him saying
"I don't authorize it." Because if it's a מודעא *moda'a* of the
person where there's no counter pressure from the other party, a מתנה
*matana* or a גט *get* is given one-sided. There's no other side,
the other party is passive, receives the מתנה *matana*, receives the גט
*get*. So the מודעא *moda'a* is just I'm just telling you, yeah,
if I give my wife a גט *get* it should never happen.
A man says "I'm giving a גט *get* to my wife, I
don't really mean to give her the גט *get*." I undercut the
consent that I'm giving to that גט *get*. So that's just גילויי
מלתא בעלמא *giyui milta be'alma*, so that's just revealing his mindset, so
that wouldn't be what we're talking about. So ואי דזביני *ve'i dizvini*,
and if we're talking about a sale, והא אמר רבא לא כתבינן
מודעא אזביני *v'ha amar Rava lo katvinan moda'a azvini*.
So and רבא *Rava* said we cannot write a מודעא *moda'a* on
a case of a sale because רבא *Rava* are you saying that
a גט *get* and a מתנה *matana* would work? And therefore it
would work even without all of these stipulations about מודעא *moda'a*. Right.
It can't be what we're talking about because those cases, you don't
need a formal מודעא *moda'a*, you can just say "yeah, I don't
really mean it" when I'm giving it to, you know, that kind
of thing. So it must be about a case of a sale.
But didn't רבא *Rava* say that by sale, you also can't make
a מודעא *moda'a* because a sale, according to רבא *Rava*, and we're
going to see on מח *Mem Chet*, you know, a forced sale
could work perhaps. Okay. לעולם דזביני *le'olam dizvini*, no, we must be
talking about a case of a sale, מודי רבא היכא דאניס *modei
Rava heichta de'anis*, so רבא *Rava* must have meant in a certain
kind of a case of אונס *ones* that you could make a
מודעא *moda'a* even for a sale, כמעשה דפרדיסא *ke'maise de'pardisa*. It's like
the case of the orchard. דההוא גברא דמשכן פרדיסא לחבריה *de'ahu gavra
de'mashkin pardisa le'chavrei*, a person made his orchard a משכון *mashkon* on
a loan for his friend לתלת שנין *l'tlat shanin* for three years.
בתר דאכלה תלת שני *basar de'achla tlat shanei*, after he had consumed
the produce from the orchard for three years as שני חזקה *shanei
chazaka* to make a claim of ownership. אמר "אם מזבנת ליה ניהלי
מוטב *amar im me'zavnat leh nihali mutav*, if you sold it to
me then great. ואי לא כבשינא ליה לשטר משכנתא *ve'ilo kaveishna leh
l'shtar mashtanta*, if not, let me hide the שטר shtar, *shtar* that
says that it's a משכון *mashkon*, ואמינא לקוחה היא בידי *ve'amina lekucha
hi beyadi*, and I'll be able to say that I just bought
it." We had a similar case a few days ago, right, with
the orphans.
What did he call it? He called it something different. That was
also a משכנתא *mashkanta* I think. כבישא לשטרא *chavisha leshtara* yeah. כבישא
לשטר משכנתא *chavisha leshtar mashkanta* what they said was a specific. That
was with orphans. So that was where it was also hard, but
they called it something. Syrian, yeah, they called it... oh that was
משכנתא דסורא *mashkanta desura*. So this, why are they calling it something
different? So here this is even more broad. There the משכנתא דסורא
*mashkanta desura* is because it's a deducted משכון *mashkon*. So over time
the principal value of the loan is deducted against the collateral and
then at the end you just kind of take back the משכון
*mashkon*.
So this משכון *mashkon* is different. This is just it's the collateral
on the loan but it's not actually... but even though it was
just the collateral, he had the right to eat the fruit. He
was אוכל פירות *ochel peirot* but he doesn't own it at the
end. So it's a similar kind of case. I think it may
be similar to the משכנתא דסורא *mashkanta desura* but here it's not
mentioned explicitly.
Okay, so the point is so he said, so כבישא לשטר משכנתא
*chavisha leshtar mashkanta* let me hide the שטר shtar? *shtar* after three
years ואמינא לקוחה היא בידי *ve'amina lekucha hi biyadi* and I'll be
able to say that I just bought it. So that's why, כהאי
גוונא כתבינן מודעא *kehai gavna katvinan moda'a*. So in that case Rava
would agree that the original owner can register a מודעא *moda'a* because
in that kind of a משכנתא *mashkanta* case it wasn't a sale,
it was a משכנתא *mashkanta*, but it was a משכנתא *mashkanta* that
could have devolved into a contested question of whether or not the
land was sold and that would be a case where Rava would
allow a מודעא *moda'a*. Can we go back to the גט *get*
for a minute, please? Sure. The גילוי דעת *giluy da'at*, but where
is the אונס *ones* there? Who is trying to constrain whom in
that case? The husband is obviously trying to constrain his wife. She
got him to come to בית דין *Beit Din* and he told
the witnesses write the גט *get* and the גט *get* is ready
to go, he has it in his hand and now he says...
he turns to the side to two witnesses and says really I
don't want to give the גט *get* and then he gives her
the גט *get*.
So you don't need a formal process of מודעא *moda'a* because she
herself could not ever protest because she has to receive it against
her will. Not that it has to be against her will but
it's only dependent on his will. So the fact that he stated
that he wasn't consenting, you don't need a formal מודעא *moda'a*, that's
a גילוי מילתא בעלמא *giluy milta be'alma* it just becomes obvious based
on those witnesses' testimony that he undercut his consent to the גט
*get* and so the גט *get* became meaningless. The question that would
happen in that case, they wrote the גט *get*, he turned to
the witnesses and says I don't want to give the גט *get*,
now right now, and now he says you know what actually I
do want to give the גט *get*. Do you have to rewrite
a second גט *get* or not? That's a big question as well
in that case because as soon as he withdrew his consent from
the original גט *get*, maybe the original object loses its halachic meaning.
Okay, so אמר רב יהודה *amar Rav Yehuda* האי מתנה טמירתא *hai
matna temirta* לא מגבינן בה *lo magbinan bah*. A hidden gift,
a secret gift cannot be collected from. So what are we talking
about, what's a מתנתא טמירתא matanta temirta *matanta temirta*? אמר רב יוסף
*amar Rav Yosef* דאמר להו לסהדי *de'amar lehu lesahadi* זילו אטמורו וכתבו
ליה *zilu atmuru vekitvu leih*.
So he told the witnesses go and hide and write the שטר
shtar *shtar* for this gift, like a piece of land or something,
a שטר מתנה shtar matanah *shtar matana* that you're writing to authorize
the transfer of ownership of this property. So he told the witnesses
go and hide and write the שטר shtar *shtar*. Presumably what's going
to happen? This is some kind of a collusion where he's trying
to give over the gift to one person but then he wants
to be able to sell it or give it to someone else
afterward
and so it's trying to manipulate the system. You're trying to be
able so that the person you're first giving the gift to will
really own it and then the second person you sell it to
publicly thinks they own it and then the person you gave the
gift to secretly is going to come and extract it from them.
You'll have benefited because you'll have the money, you'll run away to
Siberia and you'll have cheated the system. So that's why you're not
allowed to collect from this secret gift, that is the gift basically
becomes nullified because the whole purpose of creating this gift situation would
be to undercut a future sale and to disqualify it that way.
So according to רב יהודה *Rav Yehuda*, you cannot collect on this
secret gift. So ואיכא דאמרי *ve'ika de'amri*, there are those who say
אמר רב יוסף *amar Rav Yosef* a different version of Rav Yosef,
דלא אמר להו amar leihu, *delo amar lehu* תבו בשוקא *tivu beshuka*
he didn't tell them sit in the marketplace וברייתא *uvraita* and sit
outside וכתבו ליה *vechitvu leih* and write the שטר shtar, *shtar*. So
מאי בינייהו *mai beinayhu*, what's the difference between these two different versions
of what Rav Yosef said? So one was he told them explicitly
go and hide to write the שטר shtar *shtar* and one was
he didn't tell them go and sit publicly in the marketplace and
write the שטר shtar *shtar*. So איכא בינייהו *ika beinayhu* סתמא stama,
*stama*, if he didn't say anything. That's the question. Is a סתמא
*stama*, if you just said to the witnesses go write a שטר
מתנה *shtar matana* for this person I'm going to give them my
field, does that count as a secret gift or not? That's obviously
a major question. If the מחלוקת *machloket*, if the unsure case is
a case of סתם stam? *stam*, סתם stam, *stam* we usually want
to be pretty clear... Clear about because that's what happens most often.
People don't often give explicit instructions, so it's important to clarify. אמר
רבא והויא מודעא לחברתא to his
friend. So even though according to Rabbi Yehuda, who was Rava's teacher,
according to Rabbi Yehuda, you're not allowed to collect from this secret
gift because a secret gift is too secret and it's obviously trying
to manipulate the system. Nonetheless, the fact that you tried to give
a secret gift does work as a מודעא on a future sale.
Because why? If the whole purpose in me trying to write this
secret gift is that I didn't actually want to sell it to
the person I'm selling it to, so that's a מודעא. So that's
what Rava tells us, that if you tried to make a secret
gift, it works as a מודעא. אמר רב פפא, Amar Rav Pappa,
הא דרבא לא בפירוש
איתמר. ha de-Rava la be-feirush itmar. No, this thing that you just
quoted Rava as having said, he didn't actually say that explicitly. אלא
מכלל איתמר. ella miklal itmar. It was inferred based on what Rava
had said. Okay, based on what? ההוא גברא דאזל לקדושי איתתא. hahu
gavra de-azal lekadushei iteta. A man was going to marry a woman.
אמרה ליה, amerah lei, she said to him, אי כתבת לי כולהו
נכסייך
דהוינא לך, i katavt li kuleihu nikhseikh de-havina lakh, if you give
me all your property, write over ownership of all of your property
to me now before we're married, and then I'll marry you. That
was the deal. The woman says sign over all your property to
me and I'll marry you. There's a term for this, the slang
right, a gold digger, I think, right? Okay. ואי לא לא הוינא
לך, ve-i lo lo havina lakh, and she says, and if you
don't sign over all your property to me, I won't marry you.
אזל כתב לה לכולהו
נכסי. azal katvei lah le-kuleihu nikhsei. So he wrote and signed over
all of his property over to her. אתא בריה קשישא, ata breih
kashisha, his son came along, אמר ליה, amar lei, וההוא גברא
מה תהוי עלי? ve-hahu gavra mah tehevei alei? So and he wondered
to himself, the son, the son of the guy getting married, thought
to himself like, "Wait, but he just signed... my father signed away
all of his property to this woman and now what's going to
happen to me? I'm going to have no inheritance." אמר להו לסהדי,
amar leihu le-sahadei, the son said to witnesses, זילו אטמורו בעבר ימינא
וכתבו
ליה. zilu itmuru be-eivar yemina ve-khitvu lei. He told witnesses, "Go to
עבר ימינא, Eivar Yemina, some other place, and write a שטר that
was like for
selling over to him," it seems like. אתו לקמיה דרבא. atu lekamei
de-Rava. The case came before Rava. אמר להו, לא מר קנה ולא
מר קנה. lo mar kana ve-lo mar kana. Neither of them acquired
it. That is, now one of them was the woman, the woman
doesn't acquire the ownership of the properties and the son doesn't acquire
the ownership of the properties. So did he still marry? Ah, that's
the question. So we're going to see. So Rava first said it
doesn't work, the original sale, because it's a secret gift, the one
that the son tried to coordinate, and the transfer to the woman
doesn't work because the trying to make the secret gift to the
son works as a מודעא to the transfer to the woman. מאן
דחזא, man de-chaza, the one who saw it, סבר משום דהויא מודעא
לחברתה. savar mishum de-havia moda'a le-chaverta. And then whoever saw that case
inferred from it that Rava understood that making a secret sale, a
secret gift, counts as a מודעא. But Rava never actually said that.
So this is Rav Pappa clarifying the fact that while Rava ruled
in such a way that it certainly seems obvious that he thinks
that the מתנתא טמירתא matanta temirta counts as a מודעא, he didn't
actually explicitly state it as a ruling. He just said לא מר
קנה ולא מר
קנה, lo mar kana ve-lo mar kana, neither of them acquired. What
was the מתנתא טמירתא matanata temirtah
in that case? Was the father giving his property to the son
as in secret before he signed it over to the woman he
was going to get married to. And where are the words that
say that? So because he said, אתא בריה קשישא, ata breih kashisha,
אמר
ליה, amar lei, he said to his father, וההוא גברא מה תהוי
עלי? ve-hahu gavra mah tehevei alei? What about me? Like, what's going
to happen to me? I'm going to have no inheritance. אמר להו
לסהדי. amar leihu le-sahadei. He's talking about himself in the third person.
Right. He's speaking about himself in the third person. וההוא גברא מה
תהוי עלי hahu gavra mah tehevei alei meaning to me. To me.
So אמר להו
לסהדי. amar leihu le-sahadei. The father says to witnesses, זילו אטמורו בעבר
ימינא וכתבו
ליה. zilu itmuru be-eivar yemina ve-khitvu lei. Go and sign my property
over to my son and not to the woman. So he is
tricky guy. עבר ימינא Eivar Yemina is a place? Is some place,
yeah. Or the right-hand side, I don't know, the other side of
the river in town. Go over there. Go over there, right. Go
somewhere. It's hard to know who's talking. It is hard, it is
all in pronouns. It makes it tricky a little bit, yeah. So
he's being, I don't know about tricky, but he's being coerced in
a sense by both parties. Right. He wants to marry this woman
and she's made basically a very unrealistic monetary demand. Not without a
choice. But he doesn't have to marry her. He doesn't have to
marry her, it's true. No, but he wanted to marry her. But
he also wants to be good by his son. He wants to
be good by his son. Well, and he's torn between his son's
relationship with his son and his relationship with his fiancee. Didn't he
realize
that
his son... is what he's thinking. It's something like that or he's
being very, you know, you could understand it a different way. There
is a certain amount of honest leg he could be standing on,
which is to say, if he already signed over all his property
to his son, then by the time he gets married to this
woman and says, "Oh, I'm transferring all the properties that I own,"
it just happens to be none. That is so deceptive. It's very
deceptive. But it's also people get married because he doesn't have a
שווה פרוטה. shevah prutah. Well, he'll figure something out. Okay, so אמר
לאו כאן, amar lo kahn, אמר לאו כאן דחזי מאן דחזי סבר
משום דהויא מודעה לחברתה. amar lo kahn de-chazei man de-chazei sivar mishum
de-havya moda'ah le-chavertah. So Rav Papa explained whoever saw that case inferred
from it that Rava must hold that the מתנתא טמירתא counts as
a מודעה. moda'ah. Okay, בלאו הכי, be-lo hi, this sounds like a
deceptive guy getting involved in this, this is not a match made
in heaven. It's not a very good case.
Okay. בלאו הכי, be-lo hi, התם מוכחא מילתא דמחמת אונסו דכתבה. hatam
mukchacha milta de-machmat ontzo de-katvah. In this case, it's clear that it's
because he's being forced because he had actually already signed it over
to the woman before he tried to sign it over to his
son. והכא מר ניחא ליה דלקני ומר לא ניחא ליה דלקני. ve-hacha
mar nicha lei de-liknei u-mar lo nicha lei de-liknei. But in a
normal case, the reason you're doing it is not because you're being
pressured from one side or the other side, right? Here he had
actually agreed, he was perfectly fine marrying this woman and giving her
all of his money. The question then was that once his son
was pressuring him, he decided to change his mind. So that's not
the same as a normal case where actually the impetus for the
manipulation and the deception is coming from the person himself. Here it
sounds more like he's being pressured by the son. So that's the
difference and that's why you were saying that the woman was the
one who was pressuring. No, she just gave him an offer. She
said if you marry me, give me all your property, if you
don't want to marry me, you don't have to give me any
property. That's what she said. And then he agreed to it. He
said okay fine, I do want to marry you, I will sign
over all my property to you. Right, so then and then the
son comes and the son tries to pressure the father into not...
so wouldn't it be like a קל וחומר kal va-chomer that in
the other case you would say מודעה? moda'ah?
So let's see. Okay, so that's exactly the point, that is, Rav
Papa is trying to say this case is not a good proof
for our other case, the normal case, because in the normal case
the person who came up with the manipulative idea was the owner
himself. So the fact that he tried to give this hidden gift
is indicative of the fact that he doesn't want to sell it
to the person. But in this case, that idea came from a
third party, came from the son, and not from him himself. אבל
הכא מר ניחא ליה דלקני ומר לא ניחא ליה דלקני. aval hacha
mar nicha lei de-liknei u-mar lo nicha lei de-liknei. The man is
perfectly happy giving it over to the woman, ומר לא ניחא ליה
דלקני, u-mar lo nicha lei de-liknei, and the son is the one
who's upset about the transaction. So איבעיא להו. it-ba'lei-hu. So one last,
one last line in the גמרא Gemara and we'll get to the
next משנה. Mishnah. We'll leave that for שבת. Shabbos. So איבעיא להו
סתמא מאי? it-ba'lei-hu stama mai? So what about a case of סתם?
That is, what are we talking about? Look in the Rashbam, משום
דתרי לישני אמר רב יוסף. mishum de-trei lishnei amar Rav Yosef. There
were two versions of Rav Yosef going back, right? Rav Yosef had
said what counts as a hidden gift, is it when you did
say go and hide to write the שטר, or is it when
you didn't say go sit outside in the שוק shuk and write
the שטר? So סתמא מאי? stama mai? Which version of Rav Yosef
do we hold like? Ravina אמר לא חיישינן. amar lo chaishinan. We
don't worry about סתם, that is,
לא חיישינן lo chaishinan presumably that it counts as a hidden gift,
rather it would be normal, that is, if you just tell two
witnesses go and write a שטר and I'm selling this giving this
field to someone as a gift, and you didn't tell them explicitly
sit outside, that's still okay. That's a normal gift. Rav Ashi אמר
חיישינן. amar chaishinan. Rav Ashi says no, if you don't make it
explicit that the witnesses have to go and write the שטר in
public, we're actually worried that that's a hidden gift. והלכתא חיישינן. ve-hilchata
chaishinan. Our version in the גמרא Gemara sounds like the הלכה Halakhah
concluded should go like Rav Ashi against Ravina, which is just an
interesting point.
And the Rashbam says והלכתא חיישינן דלא מגבינן בה, ve-hilchata chaishinan de-lo
magvinan bah, you cannot collect from it. והלכך צריך לכתוב בתוך השטר
וכך אמר לנו כתבוה בשוקא וחתמוה בברא. ve-hilkach tzarich lichtov be-toch ha-shtar
ve-kach amar lanu ktuvuha be-shuka ve-chitmuha be-bara. You have to write in
a שטר, in a שטר מתנה or a שטר of sale, you
have to write, he said to us go write it in the
שוקא shuka and sign it בברא. be-bara. That is, it has to
be done in public. It has actually to be written in the
שטר that it was said to be done in public,
and anything that is lacking, even if it's a סתמא, according to
Rav Ashi, according to the second version of Rav Yosef, we would
actually say that that's disqualified. All right, hope everyone has a wonderful
day. I'm sorry, but I don't understand why it's not a קל
וחומר kal va-chomer that if in fact... I'm sorry, but I don't
understand why it's not a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer* then if in
fact it's a פסול *psul*. Because if it's a פסול *psul* when
it's a סתמא *stama*, then it's certainly a פסול *psul* when you
change it. So let the משנה *mishnah* just tell me the case
of סתמא *stama*, and I'll know the case of changing it through
a קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. The answer is that the משנה *mishnah*
follows the first version of רב יוסף *Rav Yosef*, where a סתמא
*stama* is actually כשר *kasher*. It's only if you change it that
it's a פסול *psul*. So there is no קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*
there. But then the question is, why did רב אשי *Rav Ashi*
have to give a second version? He gave a second version because
he had a difficulty with the way the ברייתא *braita* was taught.
And according to that second version, you're right, there would be a
קל וחומר *kal v'chomer*. But the משנה *mishnah* itself is written according
to the logic that a סתמא *stama* is not a פסול *psul*.
This is a classic way that the גמרא *Gemara* resolves contradictions between
different versions of an אמורא *amora*'s statement or between a משנה *mishnah*
and a ברייתא *braita*. Each version of the statement of רב יוסף
*Rav Yosef* provides a different framework for understanding the requirements of the
גט *get*. According to the first version, the requirement is only to
avoid an explicit contradiction, whereas according to the second version, even omitting
the name of the province is a פסול *psul*. This discussion highlights
the precision required in legal documents in גיטין *Gittin*.